Local 1199 President Leon Davis Records 5206-PR
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
Local 1199 President Leon Davis Records
1943-1975
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
Retail, Wholesale, and Department Store Union (RWDSU)
RWDSU Local 1199 Drug and Hospital Employees Union
Davis, Leon
5206-PR
14 cubic feet
14 linear ft.
Records (records).
Records of the National Union of Hospital and Health Care Employees document the evolution of the Retail, Wholesale and Department Store drugstore local, representing pharmacists and drug clerks in New York City, into an international union of non-professional and professional workers in voluntary and non-profit health institutions, including hospitals, clinics and nursing homes, as well as drugstores.
6694259
General
Contact Information:
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation and Archives Martin P. Catherwood Library 227 Ives Hall Cornell University Ithaca, NY 14853 (607) 255-3183> kheel_center@cornell.edu http://www.ilr.cornell.edu/library/kheel-center
Compiled by:
CB, September 05, 2003
EAD encoding:
Randall Miles, February 21, 2017
Biographical / Historical
Between 1933 and 1957, 1199 functioned as a drugstore local with its membership growing to 5,000 workers employed in independent and chain drugstores throughout the New York metropolitan area. With its success in organizing workers in Montefiore Hospital in New York City, the union began a massive campaign to organize workers in voluntary and non-profit hospitals in the New York area, a large proportion of whom were black or Hispanic.
In 1973, the national union was established with locals in other states, including Pennsylvania, Maryland, South and North Carolina, Connecticut, New Jersey, and Massachusetts. The union combined organizing efforts with civil rights organizations, in an effort to achieve mutual political goals. Throughout the period of these records, the union was led by Leon Davis (president of Local 1199 and of the national union) whose administration guided the union's political and social activities.
Conditions Governing Access
Access to the collections in the Kheel Center is restricted. Please contact a reference archivist for access to these materials.
Related Materials
Related Collections: 5206: Local 1199 Records 5206-G: Local 1199 Guild Division Records 5206: Local 1199 Records 5206-S: Local 1199 Executive Secretary Moe Foner Records 5206-X: Local 1199 Clippings and News Releases 5457: Mark Lillian Collection of Roosevelt Hospital (NYC) vs. Local 1199, 1962 Representational Dispute Documents 5510: Local 1199 Records 5520m: "Building a Union in the Hospitals: the Organization of Local 1199 at Montefoire Hospital, 1948-1958" Manuscript 5525: Local 1199 Additional Files 5651: Local 1199 Additional Records 5768: Sidney Cahn Collection of League of Voluntary Hospitals & Homes of New York vs. Local 1199 Drug and Hospital Union Arbitration Files 5680 OH: Local 1199 Oral History Project 5854: Local 1199 Additional Records 5871: Local 1199 Additional Records 5929: Local 1199 Bread and Roses Cultural Project Records 5929 AV: Local 1199 Bread and Roses Cultural Project Audio-Visual Materials 5929 MB: Local 1199 Bread and Roses Cultural Project Memorabilia 5929 P: Local 1199 Bread and Roses Cultural Project Photographs 5933: Local 1199 Drug and Hospital Union News files 5933 P: Local 1199 Photograph Files 5938: Local 1199 Leon Davis Additional Papers 5945: Local 1199 Additional Records 5948: Local 1199 (Rochester, N.Y.) Records 5984 AV: Local 1199 Additional Videos 5984 AV: Local 1199 Additional Videos 6016: Local 1199 National Benefit and Pension Fund Records 6062: Paul Friedman Collection of National Union of Hospital and Health Care Employees, Local 1199 Miscellany 6069: Local 1199 Bread and Roses Cultural Project Additional Files 6084 G: Local 1199 Bread and Roses Cultural Project Women of Hope Poster Sets 6140: Local 1199 Bread and Roses Cultural Project 6140 AV: Local 1199 Bread and Roses Cultural Project Audio Recordings 6140 P: Local 1199 Moe Foner Photographs 6169: Local 1199 Bread and Roses Cultural Project Files 6169 AV: Local 1199 Bread and Roses Cultural Project Audio-Visual Materials 6169 MB: Local 1199 Bread and Roses Cultural Project Memorabilia 6169 P: Local 1199 Bread and Roses Cultural Project Photographs 6209 AV: 1199SEIU Audio-Visual Materials 6209 PUBS: Local 1199 Publications 6281m: Local 1199 Biography files 6347: 1199SEIU United Healthcare Workers East Records 6347 PUBS: 1199SEIU United Healthcare Workers East Publications
Labor unions -- Health facilities -- United States; Strikes and lockouts -- Health facilities -- United States; Davis, Leon, 1907-1992; Retail, Wholesale, and Department Store Union; National Union of Hospital and Health Care Employees. District 1199; Retail, Wholesale, and Department Store Union. Local 1199 Drug and Hospital Employees Union (New York, N.Y.)
6694259
- Anti-Poverty Program, 1963-1968 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  Scope and Contents
  Contains correspondence with educational institutions, city officials, local courts, non-profit organizations, U.S. Department of Labor, AFL-CIO, and Robert F. Kennedy regarding educational, local and national programs and initiatives to alleviate poverty. Collection also contains dinner invitation, proposals, form letter, and memorandum regarding anti-poverty programs.
- Anton Refregier Mural Correspondence, 1967-1968 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  Contains correspondence with Anton Refregier concerning the design and construction of a mural for the new 1199 building (310 West 43rd Street, New York, NY).
- 1199 Ardeon Realty Corporation, 1965-1969 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  Contains financial reports, resolutions, statements of financial condition, appraisal report, and agreements regarding 1199's ownership and dealings with Ardeon.
- 1199 Ardeon Realty Corporation, 1970-1971 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  Contains correspondence with lawyers and real estate agent, financial reports, a resolution and a memorandum regarding loans and sales of Ardeon property, and the financial situation of Ardeon.
- 1199 Ardeon Realty Corporation, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  Contains correspondence and a loan guaranty agreement between 1199 and First National City Bank for a loan made to Ardeon.
- Association of Voluntary Long-Term Care Agencies, 1970-1972 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  Contains correspondence with lawyers and the Association of Voluntary Long-Term Care Agencies regarding expiration of contracts and new contract provisions.
- Building (new) correspondence, 1968-1969 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  Contains correspondence with First National City Bank regarding a loan, architect, electrician, and painter regarding building construction. Also contains memorandum on building color scheme, meeting minutes on layout of new building meeting, union expenses other than building construction. Lastly contains correspondence from an accountant regarding undocumented payments.
- Building (new) Refregier, 1968-1969 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  Contains correspondence between Leon Davis and Anton Refregier regarding completion of the mural and payment for mural design. Also contains brochure and price listing for wallcoverings.
- Charleston Hospital Strikes, 1969 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  Contains correspondence with various religious groups, union members, unions, city officials, and other organizations either asking them to donate money or thanking them for their efforts in the Charleston Strike. Also contains handwritten notes by Julia Davis recording various New York City 1199 member's contributions to the Charleston Strike. Contains financial report on how much money 1199 obtained to help the strike. Contains correspondence between Leon Davis and Charleston Strikers. Contains correspondence with Leon Davis during his time in the Charleston Jail, including a leaflet with one of his letters in it. Contains letter to UAW discussing their support in the Charleston Strikes, Walter Reuther and some "disagreements" that are going on in the labor movement. Contains correspondence with George Meany, AFL-CIO president, Walter Reuther, Henry Van Arsdale, Rev. Abernathy, the NAACP and Harvard University in reference to the strike. Contains an advertisement by Coretta Scott King in support of the Charleston Strike. Contains airplane charter and list of passengers for 1199's journey from New York City to Charleston. Contains legal correspondence and memorandums regarding what happened at the Charleston Strike. Contains telegrams from Leon Davis during the strike. Contains angry correspondence from UAW to another union regarding their representation of the Charleston Strike to the public. Correspondence with Mount Sinai Hospital thanking them for treating Mary Moultrie (president of 1199B). Contains a meeting advertisement from 1199 to talk about the strike.
- Civil Rights, 1963-1965 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  Correspondence with student group, and telegram to Davis regarding Danville, VA segregation. Memorandum to 1199 members about participating in Martin Luther King jailing protest. Correspondence with President John F. Kennedy, NAACP. March on Washington, NYC Central Labor Council, and National Urban League regarding Birmingham bombings. Contains March on Washington organizing manual, flyers, 1st plan of operation, and form letters. Contains resolution adopted at NYC Central Labor Council Civil Right Rally, and invitation to Central Labor Council's 3rd Annual Civil Rights Conference. Correspondence and attendance cards for 1199 members regarding March on Washington. Contains 1199 leaflet.
- Civil Rights, 1957-1960 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  Contains correspondence and press release regarding 1199 Negro History Week Celebration. Contains correspondence, a resolution, a public statement, a report, a subscription, pamphlets, lists, telegrams, speeches, flyers, a press release, a petition and invitations regarding conferences, meetings, dinners, monetary contributions, rallies and marches for civil rights and civil rights legislation. Contains correspondence and telegram from Davis to President Lyndon Johnson regarding civil rights, including response from the department of justice. Contains correspondence with several civil rights leaders from various different organizations, government officials and companies. Contains Leon Davis' certificate of life time membership to the National American Negro Freedom Movement.
- Civil Rights, 1960-1966 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  Contains correspondence and press release regarding 1199 Negro History Week Celebration. Contains correspondence, a resolution, a public statement, a report, a subscription, pamphlets, lists, telegrams, speeches, flyers, a press release, a petition and invitations regarding conferences, meetings, dinners, monetary contributions, rallies and marches for civil rights and civil rights legislation. Contains correspondence and telegram from Davis to President Lyndon Johnson regarding civil rights, including response from the department of justice. Contains correspondence with several civil rights leaders from various different organizations, government officials and companies. Contains Leon Davis' certificate of life time membership to the National American Negro Freedom Movement. Contains correspondence from Davis to Martin Luther King Jr. regarding Lawrence Hospital Strike, and an annual report, form letter and telegram from Dr. King. Contains correspondence with actor Ossie Davis who is upset with the magazine The Liberator for publishing an article accusing Jewish people of hurting African American's. Contains a few copies of The Liberator including the above mentioned article.
- Columbia School of Social Work, 1966-1968 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  Contains correspondence with professors, journalists, and 1199 members, plus an agreement, a list of students, form letters, invitations and flyers about the Community Organization Program sponsored by 1199 and the Columbia University School of Social Work.
- Congressional Hearings, 1948-1953 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  Contains public congressional hearings investigating communist activities in labor organizations. Contains statements by 1199 members who accompanied Davis to Washington when he went in front of the Hartley Committee. Contains Davis' testimony in front of the Hartley Committee. Contains telegrams from Davis supporters. Contains clipping about communism in labor unions. Contains 1199 press releases from 1948 when 1199 and the Bronx County Pharmaceutical corporation shut down 650 Bronx drugstores in support of Israel.
- Constitutional Amendments, 1964-1969 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  Contains proposed amendments and actual amendments to the Constitution of Local 1199. Contains correspondence regarding, and meeting minutes from meetings discussing, amendments to the 1199 Constitution. Contains ballots regarding union dues schedule for 1199 Drug Division employees, including ballot results.
- Contributions, 1964 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  Contains correspondence and form letters regarding Local 1199's contributions (via monetary donations, ticket purchases, memberships and advertisements) to various civil rights organizations and leaders (including Martin Luther King), unions and other organizations. Contains requests for contributions in the form of correspondence (including information about the organizations such as reports, financials, brochures, and clippings) press releases, contribution receipts, and invitations and flyers for events. Contains meeting minutes from an organization that mentions Davis and local 1199. Contains memorandum regarding New York Shakespeare festival. Contains form letter from Theodore W. Kheel to local 1199 for their contributions. Contains handwritten notes regarding contributions.
- Contributions, 1964-1966 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  Contains correspondence, telegrams and form letters regarding Local 1199's contributions (via monetary donations, ticket purchases, memberships and advertisements) to various civil rights organizations and leaders, unions and other organizations. Contains requests for contributions in the form of correspondence (including information about the organizations such as financials, brochures, and agendas), contribution receipts, and invitations and flyers for events. Contains handwritten notes regarding contributions.
- Contributions, 1966-1971 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  Contains correspondence, telegrams and form letters regarding Local 1199's contributions (via monetary donations, ticket purchases, memberships and advertisements) to various civil rights organizations and leaders, unions and other organizations. Contains requests for contributions in the form of correspondence (including information about the organizations such as financial need, and brochures), contribution receipts, and invitations and flyers for events. Contains handwritten notes regarding contributions.
- Contributions, 1966-1967 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  Contains correspondence, telegrams and form letters regarding Local 1199's contributions (via monetary donations, and ticket, calendar, membership, and advertisement purchases) to various civil rights organizations and leaders, unions and other organizations. Contains requests for contributions in the form of correspondence (including information about the organizations such as financial need, agenda/goals, clippings and brochures), contribution receipts, and invitations and flyers for events. Contains handwritten notes regarding contributions.
- Contributions, 1967-1968 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  Contains correspondence and form letters regarding Local 1199's contributions (via monetary donations, and ticket, membership, and advertisement purchases) to various civil rights organizations and leaders, unions and other organizations. Contains requests for contributions in the form of correspondence (including information about the organizations such as financial need, agenda/goals, clippings and brochures), contribution receipts, and invitations and flyers for events. Contains handwritten notes regarding contributions.
- Contributions, 1968-1970 (Box 4, Folder 2)
- Contributions, 1969-1970 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  Contains correspondence. memos and form letters regarding Local 1199's contributions (via monetary donations, and ticket, membership, and advertisement purchases) to various civil rights organizations and leaders, unions and other organizations. Contains requests for contributions in the form of correspondence (including information about the organizations such as financial need, agenda/goals, clippings and brochures), contribution receipts, and invitations and flyers for events. Contains handwritten notes regarding contributions. Contains a petition from the Black Panther Party.
- Contributions, 1971 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  Contains correspondence. memos and form letters regarding Local 1199's contributions (via monetary donations, and ticket, membership, calendar and advertisement purchases and conference attendance) to various civil rights organizations and leaders, unions and other organizations. Contains requests for contributions in the form of correspondence (including information about the organizations such as financial need, agenda/goals, and brochures), contribution receipts, and invitations and flyers for events. Contains handwritten notes regarding contributions.
- Correspondence "Crank Letters", 1968 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  Contains letters from Union members and citizens, attacking Local 1199.
- Correspondence "Crank Letters", 1970-1971 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  Contains letters from members to Davis, news clippings, flyers, newsletters and statements denouncing Davis and Local 1199.
- Correspondence "Crank Letters", 1972 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  Contains letters from members, news clippings, flyers, newsletters and statements denouncing Davis and Local 1199.
- Correspondence-L.J. Davis, 1964-1966 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  Contains correspondence and telegrams between Davis and various parties (such as lawyers, Mayor Lindsay, graduate students, Cornell-ILR students, government officials, hospitals, friends, arbitrators and union members). Contains news clippings. Also contains correspondence from Davis via his secretary.
- Correspondence-Moe Foner, 1964-1966 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  Contains correspondence regarding requests for materials by Moe Foner for 1199. Contains correspondence regarding requests for 1199 materials from students, other unions, government officials, etc. Also includes an advertisements and a telegram, as well as references to theater. Contains correspondence in regards to future visits and dealings with people, including an invitation to the Governor of New York to speak with union members. Contains correspondence notifying individuals of the Unions status on a subject.
- Foreign Correspondence, 1965-1968 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  Contains lists of people in the U.S.S.R and Israel to write letters to. Contains letters to unions, hospitals, government organizations and others in the U.S.S.R thanking them for their hospitality and letters regarding the anniversary of the October Revolution, and the Vietnam War. Contains original and translated correspondence between Davis and Medical Workers Union in Moscow. Contains correspondence with foreigners regarding visits and sending books and other goods. Contains a business card, a memorandum and photos.
- Foreign Correspondence, 1969-1970 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  Contains correspondence with people from Japan, Singapore, Hawaii and Poland regarding future visits and past visits. Contains lists of people's addresses in Japan, Singapore and Hawaii.
- Foreign Correspondence, 1970-1971 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  Contains correspondence with people and telegrams from Israel, Japan and the U.S.S.R concerning future visits, and current events. Also includes the agenda of a group of medical students going to the U.S.S.R. Contains correspondence regarding bringing over nurses from Singapore, including a nursing school's syllabus and news clippings from Singapore.
- Foreign Correspondence, 1972 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  Contains correspondence and telegrams between Davis and Medical Workers Union in Moscow regarding Local 1199 member's upcoming visit.
- General Correspondence, 1967-1969 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  Contains correspondence with universities, businesses, government officials, hospitals, and unions. Contains invitations, pamphlets, and flyers for events in conjunction with the correspondence. Contains a resolution from the United Public Workers. Contains a biographical sketch of Leon Davis. Contains a photograph of Leon Davis. Contains business cards of individuals who live in Tokyo, a detailed itinerary of Leon Davis' upcoming trip to Tokyo, and correspondence with people from Japan regarding his trip.
- General Correspondence, 1945-1960 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  Contains correspondence with the New York Times, lawyers, union members, unions (including District 65), arbitrators, magazines companies, prison inmates, accountants, government officials, hospitals, consultants, universities, non-profit organizations and drug companies. Contains references to Whelan Stores Corporation strike. Contains a telegram.
- General Correspondence, 1960-1968 (Box 5, Folder 8)
- General Correspondence, 1969-1972 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  Contains correspondence with consultants, arbitrators, non-profit organizations, government officials and departments, unions, union members, colleges and universities, drug companies, lawyers, hospitals, newspapers, and artisans. Also contains flyer, student rights handbook, a telegram, newspaper articles, a report from Princeton University, and a letter from Davis to president Nixon.
- General Correspondence, 1971-1972 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  Contains correspondence with arbitrators, non-profit organizations, government officials and departments, unions, union members, colleges and universities, lawyers, newspapers, and banks. Also contains flyer, a telegram, and a letter from Davis to the New York Times.
- Israel Correspondence, 1967-1968 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  Contains correspondence with Israeli groups, non-profit organizations, unions and union members, and friends regarding support for Israel during the Israel-Palestine conflict. Contains donation receipts for money given to Israeli support groups. Contains pictures, a biography of a Jewish leader, handwritten notes, a telegram and cablegram, and a collection sheet for union members to donate money for Israel.
- Israel Correspondence, 1964-1966 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  Contains correspondence with Israeli groups, non-profit organizations, unions and union members, and friends regarding support for Israel during the Israel-Palestine conflict, monetary donations, and visits to Israel and the Soviet Union. Contains donation receipts for money given to Israeli support groups. Contains pictures, postcards, and a brochure.
- Legal Opinions Correspondence, 1960-1968 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  Contains correspondence with lawyers, unions, union members, and the NLRB regarding new laws, court cases (NLRB case and Civil Court case). Also includes legal documents such as memorandums, legal proceedings, and law journal articles.
- Legal Opinions Correspondence, 1948-1960 (Box 6, Folder 1)
- Membership Correspondence, 1947-1956 (Box 6, Folder 1a)
  Contains correspondence with primarily union members but also lawyers, government officials, and newspapers and magazines regarding union issues such as unemployment insurance, complaints against fellow union members, reinstatement, union meetings, contract provisions, strikes (Liggett), elections, anti-Semitism, union member conflicts, pensions, theft, communism, and back pay. Contains press releases written by president Davis.
- Membership Correspondence, 1964-1966 (Box 6, Folder 2)